

# CONTACT

- +49 175 289 66 12
- sarahschwieger@gmx.de
- Porfyrvägen 3C, 907 42 Umeå. Sweden
- www.linkedin.com/in/sarah -schwieger1990

## **EDUCATION**

2013 - 2016 **UNIVERSITY GREIFSWALD** 

 Master of Science Biodiversity and Ecology

2009 - 2012 FRIEDRICH-SCHILLER-**UNIVERSITY JENA** 

Bachelor of Science Biology

### **SKILLS**

- Collaborative research
- Programming in R
- Meta-analysis
- Experimental design
- Teamwork
- Effective Communication

# LANGUAGES

- English (Fluent)
- German (Native)
- Swedish (Intermediate)

# **SARAH** SCHWIEGER

# **ECOLOGIST**

## **PROFILE**

I am an ecologist with expertise in experimental research, data synthesis, and large-scale analysis, focusing on plant-soil interactions and ecosystem processes. My research spans Arctic and temperate ecosystems, with an emphasis on understanding how environmental changes, such as climate warming and land management, influence plant and soil dynamics. I have experience leading collaborative projects and managing extensive ecological datasets, contributing to insights that inform climate change mitigation strategies.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

## Umeå University, Sweden

2021 - PRESENT

Postdoctoral Fellow

at the Department of Ecology and Environmental Sciences

- Managed the *Tundra Flux Database* with 77,000+ carbon dioxide flux entries from 85 Arctic and alpine tundra sites.
- Coordinated a global plant decomposition synthesis involving 41 co-
- · Led a global meta-analysis of plant decomposition in warming experiments.

#### **University Greifswald, Germany**

2017 - 2021

Research Fellow and PhD Candidate

at the Experimental Plant Ecology Lab

- · PhD in an interdisciplinary project funded by the European Social Fund
- Title: "Root dynamics in temperate peatlands under drainage and rewetting"
- · Investigated the role of roots in carbon sequestration of rewetted peatlands.
- Informed critical management practices for mitigating climate change.

#### REFERENCE

Gesche Blume-Werry, PhD

**Assistant Professor** 

Email: gesche.blume-werry@umu.se

Phone: +46 90 786 73 63

Judith Sarneel, PhD

**Associate Professor** 

Phone: +46 90 786 57 63 Email: judith.sarneel@umu.se